Guide to the Rose Weiner Papers ALBA.116
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rose Weiner Papers
1920-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weiner, Rose
ALBA.116
.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
Rose Weiner (1908-1995) was a nurse for the American Medical Bureau for Spanish Democracy during the Spanish Civil War. The Rose Weiner Papers (dated 1920-1995) contain photographs, correspondence, and personal items related to Rose Weiner’s life and her work as a nurse during the Spanish Civil War. The bulk of these materials were contained in Weiner’s personal scrapbook, which contained photographs of Weiner in her youth, Abraham Lincoln Brigade volunteers during the Spanish Civil War, and Weiner’s family later in life. Also included in these materials are nursing certificates, a small amount of personal correspondence, and letters from the American Red Cross and War Manpower Commission regarding her application to serve as a nurse during World War II.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rose Weiner Papers were donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Gerrie Karasik in 1996. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2001.150 and 2001.164. Gerrie Karasik donated additional publications and photos related to Wiener and Lincoln Brigade Volunteers. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.028.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Rose Weiner (1908-1995) was born in Lyubar, Russia into a Jewish family. As a child Rose experienced the harsh conditions of the Russian Revolution and counter-revolution while she, her mother and siblings awaited word from her father who had migrated to the United States. On September 25, 1921, Rose and her family arrived at the Port of New York before moving to Milwaukee. Weiner moved back to New York for school and attended the Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing from 1929-1932. After graduation, Weiner accepted a position at Montefiore Hospital. In March 1937 she sailed to Spain as an American medical volunteer in support of the Loyalist forces in the Spanish Civil War. Weiner worked as a floor nurse in a convalescent hospital, of which she was soon given charge. She spent several months working on the front lines before taking charge of a surgical hospital. During her last six months in Spain, she served as chief nurse of a 1,500-bed surgical and medical hospital. Weiner returned to New York in 1939 and continued work at Montefiore Hospital. Although she applied for nursing positions in the American Red Cross, Army Nurse Corps and War Manpower Commission during WWII, Weiner was never granted any of these positions, on the grounds that she did not meet physical requirements. Soon after her attempts to serve in the war, Weiner left Montefiore and began work for New York City as a Public Health Nurse. Meanwhile, she worked toward her Bachelor of Science degree at Hunter College. Weiner later worked as a school nurse until she retired in the 1970s.
Scope and Content Note
The Rose Weiner Papers (dated 1920-1995) contain photographs, correspondence, and personal items related to Rose Weiner’s life and her work as a nurse during the Spanish Civil War. The bulk of the materials in this collection were originally housed in a scrapbook. The scrapbook was dismantled, but photocopies of the intact scrapbook are included in the collection. Items contained in the scrapbook largely consisted of photographs of Weiner in her youth, Abraham Lincoln Brigade volunteers during the Spanish Civil War, and Weiner’s family later in life. It also contained nursing certificates, a small amount of personal correspondence, and letters from the American Red Cross and War Manpower Commission regarding her application to serve as a nurse during World War II. Materials added to the collection in 2017 include collected publications related to Abraham Lincoln Brigade volunteers and medical staff in Spain during the civil war. They also include photocopies of correspondence between Weiner and Fredericka Martin (dated 1969), and a photograph of Weiner in a white nursing uniform (dated circa 1928).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by format in 3 series. Folders in each series are arranged alphabetically by topic. The series arrangement of the papers is as follows:
Series I: Correspondence, 1942-1944; 1991. Series II: Subject Files, 1933-1995. Series III: Photographs, 1920s-1990s.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Related collection include the Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter Papers (ALBA 055), Mildred Rackley Simon Papers (ALBA 097), Edward K. Barsky Papers (ALBA 125), Fredericka Martin Papers (ALBA 001), and Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131).
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Correspondence.; Weiner, Rose; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy
- Series I: Correspondence, 1942-1944, 1991
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Correspondence, 1942-1944; 1991, contains letters written to Weiner from the American Red Cross, Army Nurse Corps and War Manpower Commission in the early 1940s, rejecting her applications to serve as a nurse in World War II. Also included is Weiner's reply to the American Red Cross, reiterating her qualifications. This series also includes letters written to Weiner's niece in the 1991 from two of Weiner's friends, both of whom had worked with Weiner, and photocopies of correspondence between Weiner and Fredericka Martin (dated 1969).
  - Beard, Mary to Weiner, Rose, 1942 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Byron, Rose to Karasik, Gerrie and Len, 1991 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hall, Ruth to Mary Weiner, 1944 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rosenbaum, Della, to Karasik, Gerrie, 1991 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Walson, Colonel M.C. to Weiner, Rose, 1942 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Weiner, Rose to Beard, Mary, 1942 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1933-1995
  Series II: Subject Files, 1933-1995, contains Weiner's certificate of U.S. citizenship, official documents from her service in the Spanish Civil War, certificates that registered her for nursing in New York, and collected publications related to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades. Also included are photocopies of a Weiner family scrapbook, from which the documents in this collection were separated.
  - Certificate of U.S. Citizenship, 1933 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates for Nursing (U.S.), 1932, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Service in Spain and Letter of Thanks, 1938 November - December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook: Photocopy, circa 1920s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate Transaction, 1955 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Weiner, Rose: Obituary, 1995 December (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III: Photographs, 1920-1995
  Series III: Photographs, 1920-1995 contains photographs from Rose Weiner’s scrapbook including images of her childhood, family, and as a student at Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing. There is one image of Weiner’s father in the United States prior to the family’s arrival in the United States, an image of mother Eva Rubenstein with Rose, Dora, Milton, Sam and Florence in Lyubar, Russia, and an image of the Weiner’s neighbors and cousins visiting the grave of Alexi Weiner, who was killed in a Russian pogrom. Additional photographs document the American Medical Bureau’s work during the Spanish Civil War including images of Jaime de Guzman, Captain T. Blin, medical personnel, and unidentified troops fighting for the Spanish Republican Army.
  - American Medical Bureau, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Behind the Lines: Daily Life of the Soldiers, circa1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Behind the Lines: Rest and Relaxation, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Blin, T: Captain, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Captions from Rose Weiner Display, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - de Guzman, Jaime: American Medical Bureau, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Group Portraits: Identified (Bill Gandall, Evelyn Raymond, Rose Klein), Benicàssim, Spain, 1937 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Group Portraits: Unidentified, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Medical Vehicles, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Shipboard Returning Home: Canadian Acquaintance "Larry", circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Spanish Military Hospital, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Wall Newspaper, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Weiner, Rose: American Medical Bureau, Groups and Solo, circa 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Photographs feature individuals including Lenora Temple, Mathilda Jankovic, Dulcea Hernaiz, John Jacob Posner, Rebecca Shulman, Evelyn Rahman, Epiphanio Lopez, Jose Gonzalez, Martha Mitchell, George Moser, Victor and Hirschfield.
  - Weiner, Rose: Demonstrations and Marches (outside Spain), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Weiner, Rose: Family and Friends, 1920-1954 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Weiner, Rose: Holidays, 1991-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Weiner, Rose: Montefiore Hospital, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Weiner, Rose: Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing, 1929-1932 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Weiner, Rose: New York City Department of Health, Public Health Nurse Card, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Weiner, Rose: Trips and Vacations, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Weiner, Rose: Weddings (Family and Friends), 1954, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Weiner, Rose: Youth, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Annotated Photograph and Document Reproductions (Box 1, Folder 39)